Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and today we're
going to be looking at part three of
our four part series on intermolecular
forces, which I know there's a lot of
videos on intermolecular forces, but
the big thing is that it's extremely
important for understanding it for
general chemistry and how we can
really understand how molecules behave.
So, before we talked about dispersion,
which was our weakest force of
attraction, which is something that we
find in all molecules, which is really
important to realize that everything
can do it, but it's something that has
a big impact in terms of the size, but
when it comes to polarity and having
a dipole, this has a bigger effect.
So, in this video, we're going to
focus on dipole dipole, what they are.
Hydrogen bonding, describe
that as well, and ion dipole.
We're going to look a
little bit more in detail.
Then we're going to be comparing them
and trying to understand, all right,
well, what kind of forces do they all
have, um, and then we will take a look at
what properties these all affect for our
final fourth part of the series, okay?
So, let's take a look at
this to understand it.
Okay, so dipole dipole forces are
referred to as the stickiness that holds
together different polar molecules.
So, really what this is, when you
have a dipole moment that is there,
it means it's a permanent dipole.
So, it's always a little partially
positive, a little partially negative.
It's not the same thing as ionic,
which has a complete positive and
minus there, a little different.
So, when you have something like HCl,
the electronegativity difference between
the two will cause them to interact
with, let's say, another HCl molecule.
So if they are to try to come in contact
with one another, the positive is
going to interact with the negative.
So if you were wondering like, okay,
well, how would they approach one another?
Well, the negative part is going to
come in contact with the positive,
And then they're going to be attracted
to one another to actually show, all
right, well, we have this temporary
force or that we have this force of
attraction that's happening to make
this dipole dipole characteristic.
And this is something that could
affect like the melting point, the
boiling point, the viscosity, uh, all
these other little concepts as well.
Now, dipole dipole isn't the only
form of force that's polar, right?
So there's also hydrogen
bonding and ion dipole as well.
Each of these are increasing levels
of strength as we are looking at them.
Okay, so the next one, which is
looking at, okay, we have hydrogen,
we have dipole dipole, which has that
dipole force, is hydrogen bonding.
So what is hydrogen bonding all about?
Well, essentially this is going
to be considered a special
type of dipole dipole force.
So it's very common for different
teachers to say, okay, this
falls under dipole dipole, but it
has its own special definition.
It's something that's like dipole dipole
is like stronger, bigger brother is
someone that's a lot, a lot tougher.
So one thing that we generally try to
look at here is that you need a hydrogen
atom and it has to be bound to either
a nitrogen, an oxygen, or a fluorine.
It has to be one of those
different, uh, atoms.
The way I remember that is if you kind of
look at these atoms here, so you have FNO.
Remember FNO?
You'll never forget it.
So FNO, hydrogen bonding, you'll remember
that this has this interaction here.
But keep in mind though, even though
this has the word bond in the name
hydrogen bond, it is not a real bond.
It's an interaction, okay?
Electrons are not being transferred.
It's an interaction
between different species.
So, if we were to see these different,
uh, examples here, we have water,
right, which is oxygen and hydrogen.
They can interact with one another
and actually make a dipole, or
a hydrogen bonding interaction.
We can have ammonia with another ammonia.
They can interact.
You can have HF with another one
and another one, and all of them
fit the definition, what we consider
a hydrogen bond to be, right?
It has to have either
nitrogen, oxygen, or fluorine.
In all these different
samples that are here.
Now why is hydrogen bonding so important?
Well this is something that occurs in
all kinds of different large compounds
that we find in biological systems.
So for all of you that are in health
science and biology you have to be able
to label how the hydrogen bonding works.
Which essentially there's
two definitions that we have.
There's hydrogen bond acceptors
and hydrogen bond donors.
So acceptors are what we are seeing
on essentially the right hand side
of our molecule over here, right?
So we have our oxygen is accepting
the hydrogen interaction, whereas the
donor is the side with the hydrogen.
Okay, so it's the part that
has the NOF component on it.
So keep in mind, a hydrogen bond does
not need to be with the same element.
It could be something that's different.
Right?
So here I have O and O.
That does not have to be the case.
So if I were to ask you,
okay, can hydrogen bond, can
water hydrogen bond to itself?
And the answer is, absolutely.
Right?
I showed you that earlier.
We had water talk to another water.
They can interact with one another.
What about ammonia?
Another ammonia.
And they do it as well.
Well, once again, we have that FNO, right?
Nitrogen's connected to a hydrogen.
They can also interact.
They can have that force of attraction.
But what if I try something
like trimethylamine?
Can that one interact?
Well, if I were to try to write that,
can we have a hydrogen bond occur?
Well, one thing that we can like
zoom in here, as you can see, well,
I have A carbon bound to a hydrogen,
does that fit our definition?
And then you can kind of think
like, no it doesn't, right?
It needs to be fluorine,
nitrogen, oxygen, is what the
hydrogen has to be connected to.
And that's none of them.
So remember, the hydrogen has
to be connected directly to the
nitrogen, oxygen, or fluorine.
That's not happening here.
So this is not that type of force.
It could be a dipole dipole force.
But it cannot be a hydrogen bond,
it needs to fit the definition.
What about hydrogen gas?
Can that hydrogen bond to itself?
It is hydrogen, it's in this
namesake, so could that happen?
But, if you think of H2, it's one
of our seven diatomics, right, that
we learned about in previous videos.
Is it polar, or is it nonpolar?
And being that they are all
linear, they are nonpolar.
So it's not has to be polar.
That's the other thing
that's really important.
Must be polar.
The wire hydrogen bonds.
So freaking important.
Why am I trying to spend so much
time for you to understand this?
Well, it's because if anything, it's
something that even though it might
only be 2 percent of the strength
of a real bond, it's what's holding
you together at the seams, right?
So all of your genetic information,
all of the DNA that's in your body,
every single interaction that we have
with all these different base pairs.
Is something that's being held
together with hydrogen bonds.
So without those hydrogen bonds,
your DNA would be susceptible to,
to mutations, to different cancers,
viruses, all these things that
could completely change who you are.
So all these are hydrogen bonds.
It's what keeps them all safe.
But put together to that way, it's
your genetic information is maintained
as from the next to the next.
So hydrogen bonds are really important.
It's also what holds together all the pro
a lot of your protein structures, your
enzymes, what helps keep all biological
systems in tack, but it's the most
important interaction out of all of them.
Now, what other important interaction
is also ion dipole forces.
So in order for this to happen, what
the why is here, it needs to be a ionic
compound mixed with a polar compound.
This is typically where a term
known as solubility comes from.
So like dissolves, like
trying to understand how
homogeneous mixtures come apart.
So if I put salt in water.
Well, the salt and a plus and chlorine
minus going to break apart and it's
going to interact with the water
molecules, allowing for water to
surround it on all sides or to dissolve.
This has to be an ionic compound,
dissolved water or another polar liquid.
Okay, let's take a look and
try to understand, can we label
all these different types?
So we can try to predict what, which
one's going to be the strongest
forces out of all of them and
look at the different molecules.
Okay.
So when you're comparing molecules
of this, of similar size, meaning
stuff, that's usually about the same
molar mass, you have to be able to
rank and understand what is your
strongest intermolecular forces.
So here I have from weakest
to strongest, right?
Dispersion is your lowest,
ion dipole is the strongest.
In most general chemistry and organic
chemistry courses, you're typically
looking at the first three when
you're looking at properties, but
ion dipole does feed into solubility.
So, for example, what do I mean by this?
Well, when we're trying to understand
the different sizes, we have
to keep in mind that all forces
are most likely possible here.
Um, so let's say if I have water,
it can do hydrogen bonding,
but it can also technically do
dipole dipole and dispersion.
HCl can do dipole dipole.
And dispersion.
So, to kind of go back for a second,
well, if water can do 3, 2, and 1,
and HCL can do 2 and 1, well, the way
that we can actually think of this
in terms of an analogy is similar to
how, like, subscription plans work
for different companies and different
things that you can buy online.
So, for example,
everybody does dispersion.
This is as if you sign up, make an
account on the website, you have
access to all the basic functions.
of that website.
However, there's always
stuff behind a paywall.
Everybody has to get,
has to get paid somehow.
So Dipole Dipole is like
your basic subscription.
You have your base subscription.
However, you still have access
to all of your general materials.
So if you have dipole dipole,
you also have dispersion as well.
Hydrogen bonding is like
your premier access.
Instead of paying 5 a month for
dipole dipole, you're now paying 10 a
month for a hydrogen bonding package.
Maybe you don't have ads
on this one, or something.
Well, now that you're paying for this
one, you also get what was in the Dipole
Dipole package, and you also have what
was in the Dispersion package as well.
So you have the other
tiers on top of that.
But wait, there's more!
You can also download, potentially, the
VIP access to this subscription plan.
You can pay a whopping 25 a month
to get this one, but you still
have access to hydronbonding,
dipole dipole, and dispersion.
Yeah, blind.
So the way you can look at these forces
in general chemistry is if you have access
to the strongest force, you generally have
access to the forces below it as well.
Consider it like a subscription plan
when you're trying to look at these.
I'm not trying to sell you anything,
but I'm just telling you that's
the easiest way to look at it.
So If we were to look at this
one here, so we have CH2, CL2.
The easiest way to do these is being
able to draw the Lewis structure and
to represent it in the VSEPR geometry.
You have to get efficient in writing.
So if you want to pause this
video and try to draw it
yourself, I fully recommend that.
So I'm going to show it for you.
So if I were to represent that,
right, I have C, CL2, H2, right?
And what we are going to do is you
have to label, does it have dipoles?
And one thing you're looking for is,
well, it is tetrahedral, but does
it have the same atoms on all sides?
And you can say, well, no, it doesn't.
So that means it's not symmetric, so it's
not going to allow for only dispersion.
So there is a dipole here,
so it can interact with,
let's say, another molecule.
Giving it access to dipole dipole, the
minimum, but keep in mind, that's your
tier one of your subscription plan.
So if you have that plan, you also have
access to the basic membership as well.
So if you can do dipole dipole,
you also do dispersion as well.
Okay.
So you have both of those different
forces that are available.
Okay.
So you have your basic
membership and then premium.
So if we were to do another one,
let's say if I wanted to mix
methanol and ethanol, what is the
dominant intermolecular force here?
Well, ethanol and methanol are
two organic compounds, which isn't
for anyone to M3B for my courses.
These are essentially things
that have alcohol groups on it.
And one thing that you'll see is
that there's this OH component.
If you see OH, NH, or FH, a
bell should ring in your brain.
And that's letting you know, Ooh,
these are actually capable of
doing hydrogen bonding, right?
We have this interaction here.
Here's our hydrogen bonding definition.
So what is there our strongest force?
Well, hydrogen bonds are strongest.
And is that all it can do?
Well, that might be its strongest,
but it also has access to dipole
dipole and dispersion because
all those parts are possible.
So anytime you see a molecule with
an OH, think hydrogen bonding, that's
going to be your most important.
of this individual molecule,
of these molecules.
Now, what makes this so important?
Well, when you have these polar
molecules that are interacting with
other polar molecules, this is where
that phrase, like dissolves like, is
extremely important to understand.
Polar molecules dissolve other
polar, Non polar dissolve non polar.
So if you have things that are both
dipole dipole, both hydrogen bonding,
both ion dipole, or a mixture of
those, they will dissolve one another.
If it is only capable of dispersion
forces, then that, those will
dissolve the other, only dispersion.
If they are a mixture of the
same two, typically they're
referred to as a miscible.
Or un insoluble because they
cannot be mixed together.
Alright, so if I were to ask
you, alright, well can, let's say
methane, CH four dissolve in water.
Well, CH four is tetrahedral.
It's all the same atom, meaning it's
symmetrical, so it's nonpolar, it's
dispersion water can do hydrogen
bonding so they can't dissolve.
But let's say if I change one atom,
let's say I put a fluorine on it.
Fluorine is your most
electro-negative element.
Now what do we have?
We have a dipole.
And something with a
dipole dissolve in water.
Well, if you remember, like
dissolves, like the answer is
yes, can now it's possible.
So the power of substituting one
element and make this possible.
When we are trying to look at all
these different little things,
or is it possible to dissolve?
If we were to try to look at some
of these other ones and try to
understand like, well, all right, Can
they possibly dissolve one another?
Can we understand them?
It all comes down to trying to
understand your, your forces.
The first thing you need to do is write
your geometry for all the structure
and see is it what forces are possible.
That way you can try to rank them,
understand what exactly are they
capable of when you're looking
at these different structures.
And that can sometimes be the hard part.
So thank you so much for
listening to this part.
I hope that this video helped
you understand a little bit
more of the details behind it.
Let's, we're in this, our next part
of our video, or our last part of
the hydrogen bonding series, we're
going to try to understand what
other, uh, what, what other properties
can be affected by your forces.
Thank you so much.